Unless we do something to prevent it,
ما لم نفعل شئ لنتجنبه
over the next 40 years we’re facing an epidemic
خلال الـ 40 عاما القادمه نحن مواجهون بوباء
of neurologic diseases on a global scale.
للامراض العصبيه علي مستوي العالم
A cheery thought.
خواطرة مبهجة
On this map, every country that’s colored blue
علي هذه الخريطة , كل البلدان ذات اللون الازرق
has more than 20 percent of its population over the age of 65.
تجاوز اكثر من 20% من عدد سكانهم سن الـ 65
This is the world we live in.
هذا هو العالم الذي نعيش فيه
And this is the world your children will live in.
وهذا هو العالم الذي سيعيش فيه ابنائكم
For 12,000 years, the distribution of ages in the human population
علي مدي 12,000 عام, معدل توزيع الاعمار في البشر
has looked like a pyramid, with the oldest on top.
يبدو كهرم, مع الأكبر في القمة
It’s already flattening out.
وقد بدات بالثبات
By 2050, it’s going to be a column and will start to invert.
بحلول 2050 سوف يصبح عمودي ويبدأ في الانعكاس
This is why it’s happening.
هنا شرح ما يحدث
The average lifespan’s more than doubled since 1840,
متوسط معدل الاعمار زاد بمقدار الضعف منذ 1840
and it’s increasing currently at the rate of about five hours every day.
وهي حاليا تزيد بمقدار حوالي خمس ساعات يوميا
And this is why that’s not entirely a good thing:
وهذا ليس بالأمر الجيد
because over the age of 65, your risk of getting Alzheimer’s
لان خطر الاصابه بمرض النسيان بعد عمر الـ 65
or Parkinson’s disease will increase exponentially.
او سيزداد الشلل الاهتزازي أسيا
By 2050, there’ll be about 32 million people in the United States
بحلول العام 2050 , سيتجاوز حوالي 32 مليون شخص في الولايات المتحدة
over the age of 80, and unless we do something about it,
عمر 80, وحتي نفعل شيئا بهذا الصدد
half of them will have Alzheimer’s disease
نصفهم سيصاب بمرض النسيان
and three million more will have Parkinson’s disease.
وثلاث مليون اخرين سيصابون بمرض الشلل الاهتزازي
Right now, those and other neurologic diseases --
حاليا هذه الامراض وامراض عصبية اخري -ـ
for which we have no cure or prevention --
والتي ليس لدينا لها علاج او وقايه -ـ
cost about a third of a trillion dollars a year.
تكلف حوالي ثلث تريليون دولار سنويا
It will be well over a trillion dollars by 2050.
وسيكون اكثر من تريليون بحلول 2050
Alzheimer’s disease starts when a protein
مرض النسيان يبدا حين يغير بروتين
that should be folded up properly
ينبغي ان يكون مطويا بشكل صحيح
misfolds into a kind of demented origami.
ليتمحور الي نوع من المنظومة الجنونية
So one approach we’re taking is to try to design drugs
احد التوجهات التي نعمل عليها, محاولة تصميم ادوية
that function like molecular Scotch tape,
تعمل بطريقة مثل جزيئييات الشريط اللاصق
to hold the protein into its proper shape.
لحفظ البروتين في شكله الصحيح
That would keep it from forming the tangles
التي من شأنها أن تبعده من تكوين التشابكات
that seem to kill large sections of the brain when they do.
والتي تبدو انها تدمر جزء كبير من المخ عندما تتشابك
Interestingly enough, other neurologic diseases
ومن المثير للاهتمام, بعض الامراض العصبية الاخري
which affect very different parts of the brain
والتي تؤثر علي اجزاء مختلفة من المخ
also show tangles of misfolded protein,
تظهر كذلك تشابك بروتيني
which suggests that the approach might be a general one,
وهذا يقترح ان التوجه قد يبدو عاما
and might be used to cure many neurologic diseases,
ويمكن ان يستخدم لعلاج كثير من الامراض العصبية
not just Alzheimer’s disease.
ليس فقط مرض النسيان
There’s also a fascinating connection to cancer here,
هنالك ايضا علاقه مثيرة للسرطان هنا
because people with neurologic diseases
ذلك ان الاشخاص المصابون بالامراض العصبية
have a very low incidence of most cancers.
لديهم حالات منخفضة من معظم أنواع السرطانات
And this is a connection that most people aren’t pursuing right now,
وهذا ارتباط لا يدرسه معظم الناس الان
but which we’re fascinated by.
ولكنا منبهرين به
Most of the important and all of the creative work in this area
معظم واهم الاعمال الخلاقة في هذا الجانب
is being funded by private philanthropies.
مدعومة بمساهمات خاصة
And there’s tremendous scope for additional private help here,
وهناك مجال ضخم للمساعدة الإضافية من القطاع الخاص هنا
because the government has dropped the ball on much of this, I’m afraid.
لأني اخشى ان الحكومة اسقطت الكرة على الكثير من هذه
In the meantime, while we’re waiting for all these things to happen,
وبينما ونحن في انتظار حدوث هذه الاشياء
here’s what you can do for yourself.
هذا ما يمكنك القيام به لنفسك:
If you want to lower your risk of Parkinson’s disease,
إذا كنت ترغب في تقليل مخاطر الاصابة بمرض الشلل الاهتزازي
caffeine is protective to some extent; nobody knows why.
الكافيين يحمي لحدٍ ما: لا احد يعرف السبب
Head injuries are bad for you. They lead to Parkinson’s disease.
إصابات الرأس سيئة لك. انها تودي للإصابة بمرض بالشلل الاهتزازي
And the Avian Flu is also not a good idea.
وإنفلونزا الطيور كذلك ليست بفكرة جيدة
As far as protecting yourself against Alzheimer’s disease,
في ما يخص لحماية نفسك من مرض النسيان
well, it turns out that fish oil has the effect
حسنأ, نجد ان زيت السمك له تآثير
of reducing your risk for Alzheimer’s disease.
في تخفيض الاصابه بمرض الزهايمر
You should also keep your blood pressure down,
كما ينبغي عليك الحفاظ علي ضغط الدم منخفضأ
because chronic high blood pressure
وذلك لأن ارتفاع ضغط الدم المزمن
is the biggest single risk factor for Alzheimer’s disease.
هو اكبر عامل للاصابة بمرض النسيان
It’s also the biggest risk factor for glaucoma,
كما انه من اكبر عوامل الخطر لزرقة العين
which is just Alzheimer’s disease of the eye.
وهو كمرض النسيان للعين
And of course, when it comes to cognitive effects,
وبالطبع عندما تآتي الي إدراك تآثيرات المقولة
"use it or lose it" applies,
"إستخدمها او افقدها" نجدها تنطبق
so you want to stay mentally stimulated.
إذا انت تريد ان تكون متحفزا عقليا
But hey, you’re listening to me.
ولكن مهلا, انت تستمع إلي
So you’ve got that covered.
إذا انت استوعبت هذا الجانب
And one final thing. Wish people like me luck, okay?
شيئا اخير, تمني لاشخاص مثلي الحظ, حسنا؟
Because the clock is ticking for all of us.
لأن الساعة تدق بالنسبة لنا جمعيا
Thank you.
شكرا لكم